<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="default.xsl"?>
<fr:tree toc="true" numbered="true" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" expanded="true" root="false" xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml">
  <fr:frontmatter>
    <fr:anchor>277</fr:anchor>
    <fr:addr type="user">guard</fr:addr>
    <fr:route>guard.xml</fr:route>
    <fr:title text="Guard">Guard</fr:title>
    <fr:authors />
  </fr:frontmatter>
  <fr:mainmatter>
    <fr:p>Guard is a "refillable hp" which is reduced before damage reduces <fr:link type="local" href="virtues.xml" addr="virtues" title="Virtues"><fr:strong>Vig</fr:strong>our</fr:link>.</fr:p>
    <fr:p>Restored fully upon a moment of piece after the danger has passed.</fr:p>
  </fr:mainmatter>
  <fr:backmatter>
    <fr:tree toc="false" numbered="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" expanded="true" root="false" xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:title text="Backlinks">Backlinks</fr:title>
        <fr:authors />
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <fr:tree toc="true" numbered="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" expanded="false" root="false" xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:anchor>278</fr:anchor>
            <fr:addr type="user">exposed</fr:addr>
            <fr:route>exposed.xml</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Exposed">Exposed</fr:title>
            <fr:authors />
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <fr:p>Characters who are caught with their guard down or otherwise defenceless are Exposed and act as if they have 0<fr:link type="local" href="guard.xml" addr="guard" title="Guard">GD</fr:link>.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>If they remedy their situation then they are no longer Exposed. Traps and ambushes typically catch victims Exposed.</fr:p>
          </fr:mainmatter>
          <fr:backmatter />
        </fr:tree>
        <fr:tree toc="true" numbered="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" expanded="false" root="false" xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:anchor>279</fr:anchor>
            <fr:addr type="user">mythic_bastionland</fr:addr>
            <fr:route>mythic_bastionland.xml</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Recap of Mythic Bastionland">Recap of Mythic Bastionland</fr:title>
            <fr:authors />
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <fr:p>Specifics of Combat of the wonderful system of <fr:link type="external" href="https://chrismcdee.itch.io/mythic-bastionland">"Mythic Bastionland"</fr:link></fr:p>
            <fr:p>A turn is enough time to Move and then perform an Action, always in that order.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>Players normally take the first turn of combat, discussing their plan and acting in any order they wish.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>Characters who were not readied for combat must pass a <fr:link type="local" href="virtues.xml" addr="virtues" title="Virtues"><fr:strong>CLA</fr:strong></fr:link> <fr:link type="local" href="saves.xml" addr="saves" title="Saves">Save</fr:link> or miss the first turn.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>Non-player characters react in a way that feels appropriate for current context.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>When uncertain, a character makes a <fr:link type="local" href="virtues.xml" addr="virtues" title="Virtues"><fr:strong>SPI</fr:strong></fr:link> to avoid an unfavourable reaction.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>Feats are special actions known by Knights can be performed as <fr:link type="local" href="feats.xml" addr="feats" title="Feats">described</fr:link>. Using Feats risks the Knight becoming <fr:link type="local" href="fatigue.xml" addr="fatigue" title="Fatigue">Fatigued</fr:link> which prevents them from using further Feats until they rest.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>Take the Action dice noted on your weapon(s), shield, and granted by bonuses.

  Go through the following steps in order:

  <fr:ul><fr:li>All combatants attacking the same target roll their dice at the ame time.</fr:li>
    <fr:li>If the target or their nearby allies can <fr:link type="local" href="feats.xml" addr="feats" title="Feats">Deny</fr:link> the may use it.</fr:li>
    <fr:li>Attackers amy perform <fr:link type="local" href="gambits.xml" addr="gambits" title="Gambits">Gambits</fr:link>.</fr:li>
    <fr:li>Take the hightest die remaining.</fr:li>
    <fr:li>Add extra Damage from attackers who are <fr:link type="local" href="gambits.xml" addr="gambits" title="Gambits">Bolstering</fr:link> the Attack.</fr:li>
    <fr:li>Subtract the target's total Armour score.</fr:li>
    <fr:li>The Attack causes that much Damage.</fr:li></fr:ul></fr:p>
            <fr:p>The attack's Damage is deducted from the target's <fr:link type="local" href="guard.xml" addr="guard" title="Guard">GD</fr:link>.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>If the have at least 1<fr:link type="local" href="guard.xml" addr="guard" title="Guard">GD</fr:link> remaining then they Evade the Attack.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>If it leaves them with exactly 0<fr:link type="local" href="guard.xml" addr="guard" title="Guard">GD</fr:link> then they gain a <fr:link type="local" href="scar.xml" addr="scar" title="Scar">Scar</fr:link>.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>If exceeds the target's <fr:link type="local" href="guard.xml" addr="guard" title="Guard">GD</fr:link>, the excess is deducted from <fr:link type="local" href="virtues.xml" addr="virtues" title="Virtues"><fr:strong>VIG</fr:strong></fr:link> and they are wounded.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>If they lose half or more of their remaining <fr:link type="local" href="virtues.xml" addr="virtues" title="Virtues"><fr:strong>VIG</fr:strong></fr:link> it is a Mortal Wound. Mortally Wounded targets are down and dying. They die if left untended for an hour, but can be patched up in a few moments.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>If Damage reduces the target's <fr:link type="local" href="virtues.xml" addr="virtues" title="Virtues"><fr:strong>VIG</fr:strong></fr:link> to 0, the are Slain.</fr:p>
          </fr:mainmatter>
          <fr:backmatter />
        </fr:tree>
        <fr:tree toc="true" numbered="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" expanded="false" root="false" xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:anchor>280</fr:anchor>
            <fr:addr type="user">scar</fr:addr>
            <fr:route>scar.xml</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Scar">Scar</fr:title>
            <fr:authors />
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <fr:p>Take the die that caused the Scar and roll it
again, consulting the table below for the
specific Scar caused.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>Virtue Loss through Scars is not Damage, so
cannot Mortally Wound or Slay the victim.
Scars are only gained through real, deadly
combat, not training or bloodless duels.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>
              <fr:ul><fr:li>Distress. A lucky escape: lose d6 <fr:link type="local" href="virtues.xml" addr="virtues" title="Virtues"><fr:strong>SPI</fr:strong></fr:link>.</fr:li>
  <fr:li>Disfigurement. A permanent mark: roll 1d6: Eye, Cheek, Neck, Torso, Nose, Jaw. If your max <fr:link type="local" href="guard.xml" addr="guard" title="Guard">GD</fr:link> is 2 or less, increase by d6.</fr:li>
  <fr:li>Smash. A sudden spray of blood: lose 1d6 <fr:link type="local" href="virtues.xml" addr="virtues" title="Virtues"><fr:strong>VIG</fr:strong></fr:link></fr:li>
  <fr:li>Stun. Pain drowns the senses: lose 1d6 <fr:link type="local" href="virtues.xml" addr="virtues" title="Virtues"><fr:strong>CLA</fr:strong></fr:link>. If your max <fr:link type="local" href="guard.xml" addr="guard" title="Guard">GD</fr:link> is 4 or less, increase it by 1d6.</fr:li>
  <fr:li>Rupture. Innards pierced and compressed: lose 2d6 <fr:link type="local" href="virtues.xml" addr="virtues" title="Virtues"><fr:strong>VIG</fr:strong></fr:link>.</fr:li>
  <fr:li>Gouge. Flesh torn from bone: `when you get stitched up, if your max <fr:link type="local" href="guard.xml" addr="guard" title="Guard">GD</fr:link> is 6 or less, increase it by 1d6.</fr:li>
  <fr:li>Concussion. A heavy blow numbs the mind: lose 2d6 <fr:link type="local" href="virtues.xml" addr="virtues" title="Virtues"><fr:strong>CLA</fr:strong></fr:link>.</fr:li>
  <fr:li>Tear. Something taken in violent struggle, roll 1d6: Nose, Ear, Finger, Thumb, Eye, Chunk of Scalp. When you get patched up, if your max <fr:link type="local" href="guard.xml" addr="guard" title="Guard">GD</fr:link> is 8 or less, increase it by 1d6.</fr:li>
  <fr:li>Agony. With a crack, a torturous break: lose 2d6 <fr:link type="local" href="virtues.xml" addr="virtues" title="Virtues"><fr:strong>SPI</fr:strong></fr:link>.</fr:li>
  <fr:li>Mutilation. A limb rendered lost or useless, roll 1d6: 1-2 Leg, 3-4 Shield Arm, 5-6 Sword Arm. By next Season you have a prosthetics or have learned to get by, and if your max <fr:link type="local" href="guard.xml" addr="guard" title="Guard">GD</fr:link> is 10 or less, increase it by 1d6.</fr:li>
  <fr:li>Doom. A cheated death haunts you. If you take a Mortal Wound this Season you are Slain instead.</fr:li>
  <fr:li>Humiliation. A most dolorous stroke: when you achieve revenge, if your max <fr:link type="local" href="guard.xml" addr="guard" title="Guard">GD</fr:link> is 12 or less, increase it by 1d6.</fr:li></fr:ul>
            </fr:p>
          </fr:mainmatter>
          <fr:backmatter />
        </fr:tree>
        <fr:tree toc="true" numbered="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" expanded="false" root="false" xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:anchor>281</fr:anchor>
            <fr:addr type="user">spellcasting</fr:addr>
            <fr:route>spellcasting.xml</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Spellcasting">Spellcasting</fr:title>
            <fr:authors />
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <fr:p>There is no level-up system in Bastionland, so it is natural to give some resources that will represent spellcaster ability. 

 Resource is a set of d6 dice equal to the value of <fr:link type="local" href="virtues.xml" addr="virtues" title="Virtues"><fr:strong>Cla</fr:strong>rity</fr:link>. Each time you restore <fr:link type="local" href="virtues.xml" addr="virtues" title="Virtues"><fr:strong>Spi</fr:strong>rit</fr:link> via indulging a Passion, you can regain up to two missing dice from this set.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>To cast a spell, a caster rolls any number of dice as an Action from that set and then decides what to cast. Only one spell can be cast per roll. If the spell does not state otherwise, <fr:link type="local" href="feats.xml" addr="feats" title="Feats">Smite feat</fr:link> is not applicable for them.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>Here are spells that one learns during mage training:
 <fr:ul><fr:li><fr:strong>Heat metal</fr:strong>: intricate ladder of arcane pulses rapidly heats metal until it glows red hot. Pulses should be chained together carefully, pick no less than three dice with consecutive values. If it is a piece of armour, the wearer takes damage equal to the sum of chosen dice. If it is a weapon, the bearer chooses to drop it or persevere through pain, taking half of the sum of the chosen dice. Any damage from this spell ignores <fr:link type="local" href="guard.xml" addr="guard" title="Guard">GD</fr:link>.</fr:li>
    <fr:li><fr:strong>Magic missile</fr:strong>: identical glowing bolts launch towards chosen targets, piercing bone and muscle. Pick any number of dice with the same value rolled. You can pick a different target for each bolt; it deals damage equal to the rolled value.</fr:li>
    <fr:li><fr:strong>Hex</fr:strong>: curse of misfortune impairs defense and makes the target more vulnerable. Pick three dice that have a value of one. For the remaining combat, anyone who attacks the bearer of this curse can add a die from picked ones to the dice that represent an attack before rolling them. The same die can be used by multiple attacks, but only a single hex can be cast upon any one creature.</fr:li>
    <fr:li><fr:strong>True Strike</fr:strong>: Pick any number of dice, then perform an Attack as usual. You can replace any die of the attack with any die from those you picked. Can be used with <fr:link type="local" href="feats.xml" addr="feats" title="Feats">Smite feat</fr:link>.</fr:li>
    <fr:li><fr:strong>Thunderclap</fr:strong>: Raw magical power overwhelms you and in a split second you decide to channel it through yourself or discharge it at a long range. Pick any number of dice, treat them as if it was either a single ranged Attack or a melee attack with <fr:link type="external" href="Blast">Blast</fr:link> property. If you chose melee option, always include yourself as one of its targets. If you chose ranged option you may additionally pick any one die with maximum value rolled. Discharged lightning arc jumps to another target and deals damage equal to the value of that additional die.</fr:li>
    <fr:li><fr:strong>Shield</fr:strong>: Pick two dice and add the smaller rolled value among them to <fr:link type="local" href="guard.xml" addr="guard" title="Guard">GD</fr:link> of a willing creature nearby. The shield's guard is spent before theirs. Shield's guard persists until their guard would be restored normally.</fr:li>
    <fr:li><fr:strong>Detect Magic</fr:strong>: Pick any number of dice, for each one which rolled for a maximum value you can ask a question about surrounding magic and receive truthful answer, but the amount of words in that answer can't exceed the value rolled on the die. For each other die, the answer is either yes, no or silence if the question is not applicable. Information for the answer is provided by spells around you and yourself. For example, spells usually are not directly marked by their caster and are not aware of it's surroundings beyond the spells design.</fr:li></fr:ul></fr:p>
            <fr:p>This system becomes unwieldy very fast, as the time to check the combination for a lot of spells grows in an unpleasant way. Mythic Bastionland is suited for that, as it is very easy to have a small number of spells, as majority of them are lost and forgotten.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>Also, to add even more agency, when caster rolls dice to cast a spell, additionally to casting they can choose half(rounded down) of remaining dice and discard the rest. These chosen dice can be stored to cast spells later as if you rolled them. They persist until spent, but the total amount of dice(stored and unrolled) can't exceed the value of <fr:link type="local" href="virtues.xml" addr="virtues" title="Virtues"><fr:strong>Cla</fr:strong>rity</fr:link>.</fr:p>
          </fr:mainmatter>
          <fr:backmatter />
        </fr:tree>
      </fr:mainmatter>
      <fr:backmatter />
    </fr:tree>
    <fr:tree toc="false" numbered="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="false" expanded="true" root="false" xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml">
      <fr:frontmatter>
        <fr:title text="Related">Related</fr:title>
        <fr:authors />
      </fr:frontmatter>
      <fr:mainmatter>
        <fr:tree toc="true" numbered="false" show-heading="true" show-metadata="true" expanded="false" root="false" xmlns:fr="http://www.jonmsterling.com/jms-005P.xml">
          <fr:frontmatter>
            <fr:anchor>282</fr:anchor>
            <fr:addr type="user">virtues</fr:addr>
            <fr:route>virtues.xml</fr:route>
            <fr:title text="Virtues">Virtues</fr:title>
            <fr:authors />
          </fr:frontmatter>
          <fr:mainmatter>
            <fr:p>There are three virtues for knights: <fr:strong>VIG</fr:strong>OUR, <fr:strong>CLA</fr:strong>RITY, <fr:strong>SPI</fr:strong>RIT.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>They roll d12 + d6 for each of them and keep the results.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>
              <fr:ul><fr:li><fr:strong>Vig</fr:strong>our is restored by consuming Sustenance or spending a full day in warm hospitality.</fr:li>
    <fr:li><fr:strong>Cla</fr:strong>rity is restored by consuming Stimulant or receiving guidance from a Seer.</fr:li>
    <fr:li><fr:strong>Spi</fr:strong>rit is restored by consuming Sacrament or indulging a Passion.</fr:li></fr:ul>
            </fr:p>
            <fr:p>At <fr:strong>VIG</fr:strong> 0 you are Exhausted and cannot Attack if you have moved this turn.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>At <fr:strong>CLA</fr:strong> 0 you are <fr:link type="local" href="exposed.xml" addr="exposed" title="Exposed">Exposed</fr:link>.</fr:p>
            <fr:p>At <fr:strong>SPI</fr:strong> 0 your attacks are <fr:link type="local" href="impaired.xml" addr="impaired" title="Impaired">Impaired</fr:link>.</fr:p>
          </fr:mainmatter>
          <fr:backmatter />
        </fr:tree>
      </fr:mainmatter>
      <fr:backmatter />
    </fr:tree>
  </fr:backmatter>
</fr:tree>
